<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Mark Hammond</title>
    <link>https://mark-hammond.github.io/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Mark Hammond</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 09:46:09 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mark-hammond.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Numerical dissipation strongly affects the equatorial jet speed...</title>
      <link>https://mark-hammond.github.io/blog/paper-diss/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 09:46:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mark-hammond.github.io/blog/paper-diss/</guid>
      <description>A new paper with Dorian Abbot, finished up after most of the work was done in my stint at Chicago in 2020. Something of a technical study into 3D modelling of hot Jupiter atmospheres, and hopefully laying the groundwork for a full study of their angular momentum budgets and equatorial jets in the future. Link at https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/511/2/2313/6517472.
Abstract
Hot Jupiters are tidally locked gaseous exoplanets with atmospheric circulations dominated by a super-rotating equatorial jet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The rotational and divergent components of atmospheric circulation...</title>
      <link>https://mark-hammond.github.io/blog/paper-rotdiv/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 09:46:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mark-hammond.github.io/blog/paper-rotdiv/</guid>
      <description>A new paper with Neil Lewis on a new way to divide up the atmospheric circulation of tidally locked planets! We enjoyed writing this, you can read it at https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2022705118.
Abstract
Tidally locked exoplanets likely host global atmospheric circulations with a superrotating equatorial jet, planetary-scale stationary waves, and thermally driven overturning circulation. In this work, we show that each of these features can be separated from the total circulation by using a Helmholtz decomposition, which splits the circulation into rotational (divergence-free) and divergent (vorticity-free) components.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Equatorial Jet Speed on Tidally Locked Planets. I. Terrestrial Planets</title>
      <link>https://mark-hammond.github.io/blog/paper-jet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 09:46:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mark-hammond.github.io/blog/paper-jet/</guid>
      <description>A study that I greatly enjoyed, on the formation of equatorial jets on rocky tidally locked planets. We used the highly impressive Dedalus code and came up with a mechanism for the formation of jets in idealised atmospheres. A follow-up on gaseous planets to come! Link at https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/abb08b/meta.
Abstract
The atmospheric circulation of tidally locked planets is dominated by a superrotating eastward equatorial jet. We develop a predictive theory for the formation of this jet, proposing a mechanism in which the three-dimensional stationary waves induced by the day–night forcing gradient produce an equatorial acceleration.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
